Guide to the Victor Serge Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1912-1947; Series II; 4.8; (12 boxes)
  - NOTES
    - [Nik. I i dekabristy lichnyi dopros], holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 477)
    - [Notes for In Memoriam: The Left Opposition in Russia ], holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 478)
    - "Notes sur l'U. R. S. S.," holograph, in notebook, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 479)
      Includes: notes, holograph, on two
      loose cards
    - "Notices biographiques de militants russes," holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 480)
    - "On Truth," holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 481)
      Regarding Wassily Kandinsky's work
    - "Orientation générale de la C. S. I. M.," typescript, corrected, 1943 Aug (Box 13, Folder 482)
    - "Pacte Hitler-Staline 39," holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 483)
      Includes: clipping, "Revelaciones
      sobre el pacto germanorruso"
    - "Personnages disponibles," holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 484)
      Includes: maps, holograph
    - "Perspectives sur la fin de la guerre," typescript carbon, corrected, 1944 Aug (Box 13, Folder 485)
    - [Pivert, Marceau], typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 486)
    - [Political history and political philosophy], holograph, in notebook (Box 13, Folder 487)
    - [Political notes], holograph, in noteboook, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 488)
      Includes: pencil sketches
    - [Political notes. Miscellaneous], holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 489)
    - [Problèmes du pouvoir], holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 490)
    - [Proposé à la Commission des relations internationales], drafts, typescript, corrected, 1943-44 (Box 13, Folder 491)
    - "Questionnaire," typescript and holograph, 1944 Mar (Box 13, Folder 492)
    - "Réformisme?," holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 493)
    - [Reich, Wilhelm. The Function of the Orgasm ], holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 494)
    - [Religion in Russia], typescript and holograph, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 495)
      Includes: clippings
    - [La révolution surréaliste], holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 496)
    - [Revolutions], holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 497)
    - [Séjourné, Laurette. Meetings and conversations with, in Paris], holograph, in notebook, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 498)
    - [Siqueiros, Alfaro and Latin American politics], typescript carbon, 1947 Nov 6 (Box 13, Folder 499)
      Includes: 2 clippings
    - [Socialisme et psychologie], holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 500)
    - "Solidarité internationale," typescript and carbon (Box 13, Folder 501)
    - "Sorcellerie," holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 502)
    - [Spanish history], holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 503)
    - "Sur le suicide de Maiakovski (extrait de La vérité du 9 Mai 1930)," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 504)
    - [V lesakh severa; Viatka], holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 505)
    - [A woman], holograph, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 506)
      Possibly autobiographical
  - OPEN LETTERS
    - To José Aguilar y Maya, Procurador General de Justicia de la República Ciudad, typescript carbon, 1944 Jul 5 (Box 13, Folder 507)
      From Serge, Julián Gorkin, and
      Marceau Pivert
    - To José Bergamín, typescript carbon, corrected, 1942 Feb (Box 13, Folder 508)
    - To Don Manuel Avila Camacho, mimeograph, 1942 Feb 9 (Box 13, Folder 509)
      Regarding Serge, Marceau Pivert,
      Julián Gorkin, Gustave Regler, and
      Grandiso Muniz
      Includes: press release, list of
      additional signers, copy of response
      from Camacho's secretariat
    - To los Ciudadanos, Presidente de los Estados Unidos Mexicanos, Presidente de la Cámara de Diputados, printed version, 1942 Jan (Box 13, Folder 510)
    - To Luc Durtain, typescript carbon, corrected, 1939 Aug 31 (Box 13, Folder 511)
    - To Palmiro Togliatti, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 512)
    - To "Chers camarades," typescript carbon, 1939 Mar 12 (Box 13, Folder 513)
    - To "Monsieur le Directeur de...," typescript carbon, 1943 Apr 3 (Box 13, Folder 514)
  - POEMS
    - "26 Août 28," typescript, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 515)
    - "Ailleurs il y a...," typescript carbon, 1936 Mar (Box 14, Folder 516)
    - "Un Américain: à John Reed," typescript (2 copies), 1921 (Box 14, Folder 517)
    - "Barque sur l'Oural," typescript, 1935 May 20 (Box 14, Folder 518)
    - "Berlin," typescript (2 copies), 1922 (Box 14, Folder 519)
    - "Carcasse noire du danger, écarte l'ombre et le soleil du vaste paysage des masses[?]," draft, holograph, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 520)
    - "Chant de la patience," typescript, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 521)
    - "Chernoe znam'io," draft, holograph, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 522)
    - [Chto-zh, noidem...], draft, holograph, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 523)
    - "Confiance," typescript, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 524)
    - "Constellation des frères morts," drafts, typescript and carbon (Box 14, Folder 525)
    - [Courage des collines...], holograph, 1947 Feb (Box 14, Folder 526)
    - "Au crayon un feuille rose - photo impossible!," holograph, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 527)
    - [De l'un à l'autre...], draft, holograph, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 528)
    - "Dialectique," typescript, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 529)
    - "Europe," typescript, 1921 (Box 14, Folder 530)
    - [La forme de la foudre n'est pas celle des nuages...], holograph, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 531)
    - "Frontière," typescript, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 532)
    - "Gens de l'Oural," typescript, 1935 summer (Box 14, Folder 533)
    - EMPTY FOLDER (Box 14, Folder 534)
    - [Gody, gody, bez prosheniia...], draft, holograph, n.d.
      In: Box 14, folder 559
    - "Histoire de Russie," typescript, 1934 Jun (Box 14, Folder 535)
    - "Histoire de Russie. III. Aveux," typescript carbon, corrected, 1938 Oct 12 (Box 14, Folder 536)
    - "Idylle," typescript, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 537)
    - [Krasivym sineglazym neprosto umirat'...], draft, holograph, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 538)
    - "Mains"
      - Typescript, 1947 Nov (Box 14, Folder 539)
      - Printed version, photostat, n.d.
    - [Miguel de Cervantes, le vieux Christophe Colomb...], draft and notes, holograph (Box 14, Folder 540)
    - "Mitrailleuse," printed version, Clarté, 1922 Feb 1 (Box 14, Folder 541)
    - [Monsieur Chapeau, marchand d'oiseaux...], drafts, holograph, Sep 1 (Box 14, Folder 542)
    - "Mort de Panait," drafts, typescript (2 copies) and carbon, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 543)
    - [Nash staryi leopard i ognennye ptitsy...], draft, holograph, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 544)
    - [Ne nous admirons pas trop nous-mêmes...], draft, holograph, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 545)
    - Les pêcheurs du lac," draft, holograph, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 546)
    - "Pourquoi écrire un nom," typescript, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 547)
    - "Quatre d'entre toutes," typescript, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 548)
    - [Que deviendrons-nous, ô destin sournois!...], drafts, typescript and holograph, 1912 (Box 14, Folder 549)
    - "Sensation," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 550)
    - [Solntse vkhodit i zakhodit...], draft, holograph, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 551)
    - "Sous les palmiers d'Honolulu," holograph, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 552)
    - "Soyez durs...(fragment)," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 553)
    - "Stenka Razine," typescript, 1934 Jul (Box 14, Folder 554)
    - "Tête à tête," typescript carbon, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 555)
    - "Le tireur," typescript (2 copies), 1924 (Box 14, Folder 556)
    - "Train rapide," typescript, 1925 May 15 (Box 14, Folder 557)
    - [Tsyplenok dutyi...], draft, holograph, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 558)
      Includes: French translation
    - [Ty skazhi, skazhi mne tikho...], draft, holograph, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 559)
    - "Vieille femme," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 560)
    - "Ville," typescript, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 561)
    - [Voici les espaces des mondes...], drafts, holograph, 1947 Jan 19 (Box 14, Folder 562)
    - Fragments, drafts, holograph, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 563)
  - REVIEWS
    - Baeck, Leo. The Pharisees, and Other Essays, typescript (Box 14, Folder 564)
    - Dallin, David J. and Boris I. Nicolaevsky. Forced Labor in Soviet Russia
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 565)
      - Clipping of printed version, Revista israelita, 1947 Oct
    - Esprit, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 566)
      See also: Box 14, folder 568
    - Fromm, Eric. Escape from Freedom, clipping of printed version, New Essays, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 567)
    - Horizon
      - Typescript carbon (French), n.d. (Box 14, Folder 568)
      - Clipping of printed version (Spanish), Revista israelita, 1947 Apr
    - Jaeger, Werner. Paideia: fondo de cultura económica, clipping of printed version, Revista israelita, 1946 Sep (Box 14, Folder 569)
    - Kafka, Franz. Erzahlungen und kleine Prosa beschreibung eines Kampfes, typescript carbon, corrected (Box 14, Folder 570)
    - Malaquais, Jean. Journal de guerre, drafts, typescript carbon, corrected, 1944 (Box 14, Folder 571)
    - Modern Review, clipping of printed version, Revista israelita, 1947 Oct (Box 14, Folder 572)
    - Partisan Review, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 573)
    - Picón-Salas, Mariano. De la conquista à la indépendencia, clipping of printed version, Revista israelita, 1946 May (Box 14, Folder 574)
    - Ramos, Arthur. Poblaciones del Brasil; Leopoldo Benítes Vinueza. Argonautas de la selva; Augusto Guzmán. Tupaj Katari, clipping of printed version, Revista israelita, 1946 Aug (Box 14, Folder 575)
    - Russell, Bertrand. A History of Western Philosophy
      - Typescript (French), corrected, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 576)
      - Clipping of printed version (Spanish), Revista israelita, 1946 Jun
    - Sington, Derrick and Arthur Weidenfeld. The Goebbels Experiment: A Study of the Nazi Propaganda Machine, typescript carbon, corrected, 1944 (Box 14, Folder 577)
    - Werth, Leon. Deposition, typescript carbon, corrected (Box 14, Folder 578)
  - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
    - Aragon, Louis. "Il nous faut un Guépéou," clipping of printed version of poem, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 579)
    - Durtain, Luc. "A certains écrivains communistes," clipping of printed version, 1939 Aug 30 (Box 14, Folder 580)
    - Favre, J. "Remarques sur la situation en Espagne," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 581)
    - Fraenkel, Fritz. "Sobre la psicología del nacional-socialismo" (written with Herbert Lennhoff), typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 582)
      Includes: German version, "Ueber die
      Psychologie des Nationalsozialismus,"
    - Gordeaux, Paul. "Le crime ne paie pas: l'assassinat du tsar Alexandre II," cartoon with text (2 copies), printed version (Box 14, Folder 583)
    - Gorkin, Julián. "Carta abierta à Julio Alvarez del Vayo," typescript carbon (2 copies), 1942 Apr 1 (Box 14, Folder 584)
    - Independent Labour Party (Great Britain). "Proposiciones del Independent Labour Party (I. L. P.) de Inglaterra relativas à los problemas consecuentes à un nuevo movimiento socialista internacional," typescript carbon (Box 14, Folder 585)
    - Laurat, Lucien. "L'impérialisme capitaliste classique," clipping (fragment) of printed version, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 586)
    - Lennhoff, Herbert. "Fritz Fraenckel," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 587)
      Includes: letter from Serge to The Call, [19]44 Jun 26
    - Melter, Luis. "Los problemas del socialismo en nuestro tiempo," typescript mimeograph, 1944 Mar (Box 14, Folder 588)
    - Moroz, G. "La guerre civile en Russie (quelques pages d'histoire)," galley proofs, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 589)
    - Pivert, Marceau. [En ce qui me concerne...], typescript, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 590)
    - Romualdi, Serafino. "Contestacion à las calumnias de los communistas," typescript mimeograph, 1947 Jun 17 (Box 14, Folder 591)
    - Rous, Jean. "Les 'méthodes' de Léon Trotsky," printed version, La voie de Lénine, 1939 Mar (Box 14, Folder 592)
    - Trotsky, Leon
      - "Beaucoup de bruit autour de Kronstadt," printed version, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 593)
      - "Encore sur la répression de Kronstadt," printed version, 1938 Jul 6 (Box 14, Folder 594)
      - "I Stake My Life!," printed version, 1937 Feb 9 (Box 14, Folder 595)
      - "Matériaux du 10-e Congrès du Parti Communiste Russe," galley proofs, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 596)
    - Wollenberg, Erich. "Grenzverwischung zwischen G. P. U. und Gestapo," typescript carbon (Box 14, Folder 597)
- Subject Files, 1935-1947; Series III; 0.8; (2 boxes)
  Series III, Subject Files, is arranged alphabetically.
  - Alter, Victor and Henryk Erlich. Deaths of: clippings, 1943 (Box 15, Folder 598)
  - Black terror: clippings, 1937 (Box 15, Folder 599)
  - Castillo Ramírez, Fernando. Death of: clippings, 1943 (Box 15, Folder 600)
  - Centro Cultural Ibero-Mexicano: poster (3 copies) and pamphlet for tribute to Carlo Tresca, Victor Alter, and Henryk Erlich, 1943 Apr 10 (Box 15, Folder 601)
  - Fraenkel, Federico (Fritz). Death of: clippings, 1944 (Box 15, Folder 602)
  - Free German Association: report, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 603)
  - G. P. U.
    See: Soviet Union. Obedinennoe gosudarstvennoe politicheskoe upravlenie, Box 16, folder 615
  - Lombardo Toledano, Vicente
    - Copies of documents, typescript carbon and galley proofs, 1935-44, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 604)
    - Clippings, 1943-47, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 605)
  - Mexican and South American politics: clippings, 1937-46, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 606)
  - Mundo Socialismo y Libertad: poster for pro-socialist demonstration, Jun 15 (Box 15, Folder 607)
  - Navashin, Vasil'enko; G. P. U.: clippings, 1937 (Box 15, Folder 608)
  - Newspaper pictures: clippings, 1936-39, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 609)
  - Red army; Tukhachevskii: clippings, 1937 (Box 15, Folder 610)
  - Refugees: correspondence, notes, 1941-46, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 611)
  - Ruehle, Otto: clippings, notes, drafts, 1943, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 612)
    See also: Box 16, folders 620-621
  - Russian clippings, 1937-42, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 613-614)
  - Soviet Union. Obedinennoe gosudarstvennoe politicheskoe upravlenie: clippings, 1941-47, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 615)
  - Tresca, Carlo. Death of: clippings, 1943 (Box 16, Folder 616)
  - Trotsky, Leon
    - Clippings, 1934-47, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 617)
    - Articles and press releases, 1937-50, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 618)
    - Poster for Trotsky Memorial Meeting, [1941] Aug 22 (Box 16, Folder 619)
    - Fourth International, "Trotsky Memorial Number", 1941 Aug
  - Trotsky, Leon. Commission of Inquiry into the Charges Made Against Leon Trotsky in the Moscow Trials
    - Correspondence, 1937-38, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 620)
    - Press releases, meeting minutes, reports, and documents, 1937, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 621)
    - Clippings, 1937, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 622)
- Personal Papers and Memorabilia, 1916-1947; Series IV; 0.4; (1 box)
  - VICTOR SERGE
    - Immigration and identification documents, 1916-42, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 623-624)
    - Description of deposit of manuscripts by Serge with "La Censure du Commissariat du Peuple à l'Instruction Publique" in Moscow, 1936 Apr 14, 1936 Jun 9 (Box 17, Folder 625)
    - Clippings and transcripts of interviews and biographical articles, 1936-46, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 626)
    - Address book, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 627)
      Includes: others' business cards
    - Biographical notes, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 628)
    - Book inventory, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 629)
    - Business card, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 630)
    - Death mask, metal, by Victor Trapote, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 631)
    - Wallet, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 632)
  - KIBALCHICH FAMILY
    - Kibalchich, Jeannine. Certificate regarding Jeannine's wartime placement, 1940 Feb 26 (Box 17, Folder 633)
    - Kibalchich, Liouba Roussakova. Health and identification documents and receipts, 1932-45, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 634)
    - Kibalchich, Vlady
      - Copy of birth certificate, 1920 (Box 17, Folder 635)
      - Two black and white photographs of Vlady and a painting (Box 17, Folder 636)
        Each photograph shows a different
        painting
      - Two pencil sketches possibly by Vlady, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 637)
  - OTHER MEMORABILIA
    - Death mask (metal) of Vsevolod Mikhailovich Eikhenbaum, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 638)
      Outside of mask signed "Volin"
      Previously identified as a mask of
      Leon Trotsky
    - Blank Russian postcards, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 639)
    - Dried flower, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 640)
    - Fabric pocket, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 641)
    - Handkerchief (Box 17, Folder 642)
- Envelopes, n.d.; Series V; 1; (3 boxes)
  - Envelopes, n.d. (Box 18)
  - Envelopes, n.d. (Box 19)
  - Envelopes, n.d. (Box 20)
- Materials Collected by Vlady Kibalchich, 1949-1994; Series VI; 0.8; (2 boxes)
  Series V, Materials Collected by Vlady Kibalchich,
  is organized into five subseries, Correspondence,
  Serge's Writings, Reviews of Serge's Writings,
  Translations of Serge's Writings, Writings about Serge,
  and Writings by Others. Correspondence is arranged by
  type of letter, and then chronologically. The remaining
  subseries are arranged by author or by title.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Kibalchich, Vlady
      - Letters to
        - Pathfinder Press (photostat), [1972 Nov 29?] (Box 21, Folder 643)
          Enclosed in letter to [?],
          1972 Nov 29
        - Monsieur Temez, n.d.
      - Letters from
        - The Original Press, 1965 Oct 9 (Box 21, Folder 644)
        - Remi Hewens, 1966 Feb 28
        - P. Mounier, 1972 Jan 12
          Includes: photocopies of letters
          from Emmanuel Mounier to Serge,
          1940-47
        - Marguerite Bonnet, 1972 Oct 13
        - Ernest Mandel, 1972 Nov 20
        - Peter [Sedgwick?], 1979 Aug 1
        - Éditions du Seuil, 1980 May 27
        - Gustav and Margaret Regler
        - Editions François Maspero, n.d.
      - Receipt from Pérez Siliceo, 1971 Aug 2 (Box 21, Folder 645)
    - Serge, Victor
      - Letters to
        - Magdeleine Marx (photocopy), [19]36 May, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 646)
        - [?] (photocopies), [19]47 Jul 11, Sep 26, n.d.
      - Letters from
        - Leon Trotsky, 1936 Jun 24, Aug 22, transcription by Vlady Kibalchich, holograph, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 647)
    - Third party letters
      - Jean Rière to Silverio Canada, 1978 Jul 26 (photostat), n.d. (Box 21, Folder 648)
      - United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation to Susan C. Weissman. Bound volume of photocopies of documents concerning Serge obtained by Weissman through the Freedom of Information Act, 1987 Apr 24 (Box 21, Folder 649)
  - SERGE'S WRITINGS
    - "Adèu a Andreu Nin", 1990
      In: Box 22, folder 687
    - L'an I de la révolution russe, portion of Chapter 6, printed version, The New International, 1948 Nov (photocopy), n.d. (Box 21, Folder 650)
    - "L'anniversaire du 15 janvier: Karl Liebknecht et Rosa Luxembourg", n.d.
      In: Box 21, folder 657
    - "Asechanzas en España", 1990
    - "Au seuil d'une révolution"
      - "La 'retraite d'octobre' en Allemagne," printed version, Clarté, 1924 Feb 1 (photocopy), n.d. (Box 21, Folder 651)
      - "Le P. C. allemand se critique lui- même," printed version, Clarté, 1924 Feb 15 (photocopy) (Box 21, Folder 652)
    - La batalla: clippings (photostats), n.d. (Box 21, Folder 653)
      "El fin de los escritores
      thermidorianos,
      "Puchkin, un recuerdo al poeta que
      lucho contra el despotismo zarista,"
      1937 Feb 11
      "La revolución salvadore," 1923 Aug 17
    - "Le bilan d'une année"
    - "¿A dónde va Stalin?", 1990
    - "Los escritos y los hechos", 1990
    - "Guerre de transformation sociale," typescript, corrected, 1942 Jun (photocopy), n.d. (Box 21, Folder 654)
    - "Literatura de postguerra", 1990
    - Mémoires d'un révolutionnaire, clippings of serial version, Combat, 1949-50 (Box 21, Folder 655)
    - "Necesidad de una renovación del socialismo", 1990
    - "Notes d'Allemagne," printed version, Bulletin communiste, 1923 Oct-Nov (photocopy), n.d. (Box 21, Folder 656)
    - "Notes d'Allemagne," printed version, La correspondence internationale, 1923 Jan-Nov (photocopy) (Box 21, Folder 657)
    - "Nouvelles d'Allemagne", n.d.
    - [Peregrupuvannia revoliutsiinikh frantsuz'kikh pis'mennikiv], printed version, Vaplite, 1926 (photocopy), n.d. (Box 21, Folder 658)
      Ukrainian translation of Serge's
      work
    - "El recuerdo de Vladimir Illitch", 1990
    - "Réponse à Trotsky," printed version (photocopy, 2 copies), n.d. (Box 21, Folder 659)
    - "Signification de cette guerre: guerre de transformation du monde," typescript, corrected, [19]42 Nov (photocopy) (Box 21, Folder 660)
    - Tierra y libertad: clippings (photostats), n.d. (Box 21, Folder 661)
      "Momentos extremos," 1917 Apr 18
      "Octavio Mirbeau," 1917 Mar 3
      "Un zar cae," 1917 Apr 4
    - "Vers un renouvellement du socialisme?," transcription by Emilio Brodziak, typescript, 1994 Apr
      In: Box 22, folders 677-678
    - "La vida y la muerta de Leon Trotski", 1990
    - "Vladimir Korolenko," printed version, Bulletin communiste, 1922 Jan 3 (photocopy), n.d. (Box 21, Folder 662)
  - REVIEWS OF SERGE'S WRITINGS
    - L'affaire Toulaév, 1949-55, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 663)
    - L'an I de la révolution russe, 1970-71, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 664)
      Includes: advertisement
    - Les années sans pardon, 1971-81, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 665)
      Includes: advertisements
    - Carnets, 1986 (Box 21, Folder 666)
    - Ce que tout révolutionnaire doit savoir de la répression, 1970-71 (Box 21, Folder 667)
    - Les derniers temps, 1952 (Box 21, Folder 668)
    - Mémoires d'un révolutionnaire, 1951-68, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 669)
    - Naissance de notre force, 1967-79 (Box 21, Folder 670)
    - Les révolutionnaires, 1967 (Box 21, Folder 671)
    - Vie et mort de Trotsky, 1951-79, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 672)
    - Ville conquise, 1970-79, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 673)
  - TRANSLATIONS OF SERGE'S WRITINGS
    - Costa-Iscar
      - [Unidentified], typescript (photocopy), n.d. (Box 22, Folder 674)
    - Palomar, María and Emilio Brodziak
      - "El drama de la conciencia moderna," typescript, 1994 Mar
      - "Economía dirigida y democracia," typescript, 1994 Jun (Box 22, Folder 675)
      - "¿Hacia una renovación del socialismo?," typescript, 1994 May
      - "Para La nación 26 de mayo de 1941," typescript, 1994 Mar
      - "Poderío y limitaciones del marxismo," typescript, 1994 Jun (Box 22, Folder 676)
  - WRITINGS ABOUT SERGE
    - Aguilar Mora, Manuel
      - "Serge y la conciencia socialista de fin de siglo," typescript, 1993 Jul 22
      - "Víctor Serge y la hazañas de la esperanza," typescript, 1994 Mar 9
      - "Víctor Serge y la literatura del siglo XX," typescript, 1993 Jul 15
    - Andrade, Juan
      - "Recuerdo", 1990
    - Brodziak, Emilio
      - " El caso Tuláyev de Víctor Serge," typescript, 1994 Jan 14
      - "Trabajos de y sobre Víctor Serge," typescript (bound), 1994 (Box 22, Folder 677-678)
        "¿Hacia una renovación del
        socialismo?" by Victor Serge
        "Vers un renouvellement du
        socialisme?" by Victor Serge
        "Para La nación " by Victor Serge
        "El drama de la conciencia
        moderna" by Victor Serge
        "Víctor Serge y su novela El caso Tuláyev " by Yuri Páporov
        "Víctor Serge y la literatura del
        siglo XX" by Manuel Aguilar Mora
        "Serge y la conciencia socialista de
        fin de siglo" by Manuel Aguilar Mora
        "Víctor Serge y la hazañas de la
        esperanza" by Manuel Aguilar Mora
        " El caso Tuláyev de Víctor
        Serge" by Emilio Brodziak
        "A propósito de El caso Tuláyev "
        by Jaime Labastida
        Serge" by Román Munguía Huato
        " El caso Tuláyev. Notas de
        lectura" by Leo Eduardo Mendoza
        [Untitled] by Vlady Kibalchich
        "Versiones de la historia: Boris
        Yeltsin, Víctor Serge y la
        rebelión de Kronstadt" by Richard
        Greeman
        "Erotemas socialistas" by Vlady